## **Aleksandr Sokolov**

Data scientist

Belgrade, Serbia (residence permit) | +(381)29448907 | sokaa2011@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub

**SUMMARY:** I have 4 years of commercial experience in data science, enhanced by 2 additional years of specialized training in Data Science, bring a strong background in mathematics and thrive on turning complex data into actionable insights. I have experience in quality Exploratory Data Analysis (EDA) and practical applications of various machine learning algorithms, attentive to potential data leaks, proficient in data report visualization, and have a solid command of SQL. Hold the title of a Kaggle Expert and placed 15th in Yandex ML training from thousands of participants.

I have been recognized with the 'Teacher of the Year' award among immigrants for my work in teaching mathematics to high school students in Israel. My teaching experience spans simplifying complex mathematical topics such as calculus, optimization, helping students and peers grasp difficult concepts.

Additionally, my professional qualities include strong business acumen accumulated over 15 years of business experience in managerial sales positions at major retailers and IT companies, including P&G, 2GIS and Coca-Cola.

**SKILLS:** Python | Jupyter | Scikit-Learn | Catboost | LAMA | AutoWoE | SHAP | Pandas | NumPy | Matplotlib | TensorFlow | Keras | PyTorch | MLflow | Mage | PySpark | Polars | Git + pre-commit | GitLab Cl/CD | Docker | Airflow | Flask | Streamlit | Evidently | Grafana | PostgreSQL | MySQL | AWS | GCP | S3 | Pytest | black | pylint | Agile | A/B Testing | User Metrics | Data-driven Decision Making | Customer Interviews | Presentation Skills | Critical Thinking

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Sber** (June 2021 – May 2024)

Largest bank leading tech innovator specializing in AI and digital ecosystems b2b and b2c

#### Data scientist

- Developed an ML model for predicting customer flow at Multifunctional Service Centers, reducing queue waiting time by 20%. Utilized optimization algorithms and NumPy for efficient data preprocessing in high-load systems. The forecast covers up to 2 months ahead, with half-hour intervals. MAPE < 18%.</li>
- Achieved a nearly 80% reduction in the second-month churn rate of new sales trainees by analyzing data on their behavior in the onboarding system and interactions with the gamification system, identifying patterns, and providing insights to adjust gamified onboarding scenarios.
- Focused on Classic ML, Time Series, NLP and predictive modeling algorithms. The 360-degree evaluation highlighted my business acumen, clear interpretation of results, and visualization of reports for stakeholders, as well as the ability to identify errors and optimize 'other people's' code (legacy).

## ROLF (November 2020 – April 2021)

Leading automotive dealership offering vehicle sales and services b2b and b2c

### **Data scientist**

- Computer Vision: Created a CNN model for classifying cars based on photographs, increasing the conversion rate from website visits to trade-in deals by nearly 75% through initial online valuation based on photos.
- Parsing + ML: Scraped all listings from auto.ru in Moscow and developed a car market value prediction model, doubling the speed of trade-in car acceptance from 1 hour to 30 minutes and increasing net profits by 12%. The model provided managers with optimized pricing recommendations, while allowing them to make independent pricing decisions.

## **Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology** (September 2019 – April 2021)

### Student

Completed Data Science, which covered advanced topics in ML, DL, NLP, and CV. The program emphasized
practical experience in building robust data pipelines, distributed computing, and cloud infrastructure. Additionally,
gained proficiency in Python programming.

## ORT Guttman School Network (February 2014 – July 2019)

### High school mathematics teacher

- Was acknowledged as a Best New Teacher of the Year in the school network.
- Mentored a student team in the robotics competition 'First Lego League'.

# **Procter & Gamble Distribution Management System CJSC** (May 2008 – August 2013)

### **Business development director**

• Ensured the successful implementation of "The Baikal" federal IT project, enhancing logistics transparency between P&G distributors and the Sales Department.

- Achieved above-average market share growth in major product categories compared to the previous year, as reported by Nielsen.
- Led the acquisition of a major distributor, doubling the territory and increasing revenue by 45%

### **2GIS** (September 2004 – May 2008)

Leading digital mapping provider with business directories and geolocation for B2B and B2C.

## **Business development director**

- Ensured high accuracy in monthly sales planning, maintaining a forecast error rate below 7%.
- Developed and implemented a new remuneration and comprehensive performance evaluation system for sales managers, increasing employee satisfaction by 40% and contributing to a 15% rise in the company's annual profits

## Coca-Cola HBC Eurasia (May 2002 – September 2004)

## **Manager Supervisor**

- Analyzed and executed KPIs while managing orders and preparing territories for executive visits, demonstrating strong analytical skills and consistently meeting performance targets
- Mentored a team of five client account managers, providing training on route sales techniques and ensuring the achievement of monthly sales targets

### **EDUCATION**

- Master's degree in Artificial Intelligence, MIPT
- Bachelor's degree in Mathematics and Mechanics, NSU
- Master of Education in Mathematics, Oranim College, Israel
- Master of Business Administration, Open University, UK

### **CERTIFICATION/COURSES/LICENSES**

- Data Science Bootcamp, Yandex Practicum (May October 2023)
- Image Segmentation with TensorFlow, NVIDIA (September 2020 December 2020)

## **ADDITIONAL INFORMATION**

• Languages: Russian (native), English (Professional working proficiency)